Guide to the Harold C. Conklin Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Harold C. Conklin papers
1887-2008
MS 1956
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
78.42
(169 containers)
The papers comprise correspondence, maps, and topical files documenting the research of anthropologist Harold C. Conklin and his colleagues, particularly in the area of linguistics and focusing on the Philippines. The papers also represent Conklin's professorial, curatorial, and administrative work at Yale University.
Conklin, Harold C., 1926-2016
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Harold C. Conklin, 2009.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
Harold C. Conklin Philippine Collection (AFC 2001/007), Archive of Folk Culture, American Folklife Center, Library of Congress.
Biographical / Historical
Harold C. Conklin (born 1926) received his B.A. degree from the University of California, Berkeley, in 1950 and his Ph.D. from Yale University in 1955. He taught anthropology at Columbia University from 1954 until 1962, at which time he joined the Yale faculty. Conklin served as chair of the Department of Anthropology, curator of Anthropology, and director of Graduate Studies, as well as director of the Division of Anthropology at the Peabody Museum of Natural History. An emeritus professor, he retired from Yale in 1996. He was also the Frank Muzzy Crosby Professor Emeritus of the Human Environment. Conklin pioneered research in the field of ethnoscience, a discipline dealing with the way in which inhabitants of a particular area understand and treat their environment. His research focused primarily on ecology, ethnology, and linguistics in Southeast Asia, particularly the Philippines, and he authored numerous publications and articles in his field. Conklin died on February 18, 2016.
Scope and Contents
The papers comprise personal and professional correspondence, maps, and topical files, documenting the research of Conklin and his colleagues, particularly in the area of language in the Philippines. Maps were created in part by the American Geographical Society and the Army Map Service. The Topical Files include professional events and organizations in which Conklin participated; research materials of colleagues Leonard Bloomfield, Frederick Russell Eggan, and Robert B. Fox; and materials relating to the Tasaday Controversy, in which the Tasaday, an indigenous people of Mindanao, a Philippine island, were considered in the 1970s-1980s to be the last vestiges of a stone age culture. Anthropologists and journalists questioned the validity of this claim. Additional files document Conklin's professorial, curatorial, and administrative activities at Yale, particularly in the Department of Anthropology and the Peabody Museum of Natural History.
Conditions Governing Access
Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in three series: I. Correspondence, 1944-2005. II. Maps, 1908-1977. III. Topical Files, 1897-1998.
Anthropological linguistics; Ilokanos (Philippine people); Iloko language; Tagalog language; Tasaday (Philippine people); Tinggian language; Ifugao (Philippines); Philippines; Bloomfield, Leonard, 1887-1949; Conklin, Harold C., 1926-2016; Eggan, Fred, 1906-1991; Fox, Robert B., 1918-1985
- Correspondence, 1944-2005; Series I
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged as it was received from Harold Conklin, in rough chronological order based on meaningful periods in his career.
  - Philippine Islands, 1944-1948 (Box 1, Folder 1-6)
  - Berkeley, 1949-1950 (Box 1, Folder 7-12)
  - New Haven, 1950-1952 (Box 1, Folder 13-17)
  - New Haven Christmas cards, 1950-1952 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Yg.I, 1952-1954 (Box 2, Folder 1-5)
  - New Haven-New York, 1954-1955 (Box 2, Folder 6-10)
  - New York, 1956-1957 (Box 2, Folder 11-14)
  - Yg II, 1957-1958 (Box 2, Folder 15-18)
  - New York, 1959-1962 (Box 3, Folder 1-18)
  - New York, 1961-1962 (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
  - Bayninan, 1962-1963 (Box 4, Folder 3-8)
  - New Haven, 1963-1965 (Box 4, Folder 9-21)
  - New Haven, 1965-1967 (Box 5, Folder 1-15)
  - M-Z, 1967-1968 (Box 6, Folder 1-4)
  - Bayninan, 1968-1969 (Box 6, Folder 5-9)
  - A-W, 1969-1971 (Box 6, Folder 10-19)
  - A-W, 1971-1973 (Box 7, Folder 1-7)
  - A-Z, 1973-1975 (Box 7, Folder 8-15)
  - A-D, 1975-1977 (Box 7, Folder 16-17)
  - E-Z, 1975-1977 (Box 8, Folder 1-6)
  - A-Y, 1977-1979 (Box 8, Folder 7-12)
  - A-Z, 1979-1981 (Box 8, Folder 13-18)
  - A-Z, 1981-1985 (Box 9, Folder 1-12)
  - A-Y, 1986-1988 (Box 10, Folder 1-9)
  - A-I, 1989-1991 (Box 10, Folder 10-14)
  - K-W, 1989-1991 (Box 11, Folder 1-4)
  - A-Z, 1992-1993 (Box 11, Folder 5-11)
  - A-Z, 1994-1995 (Box 12, Folder 1-4)
  - A-P, 1996-2005 (Box 12, Folder 5-13)
  - Q-Z, 1996-2005 (Box 13, Folder 1-5)
- Maps, 1908-1977; Series II
  Scope and Contents
  Maps deal primarily with land usage, district drainage, and related topics in the Philippine islands.
  - Luzon, Philippines, 1908; M-678 (Box 14)
    1977 enlargement of a 1908 Hodgson and Briesmeister map (1: 2500,000; 1: 1,115,000).
  - Bayninan, 1977; M-1022 (Box 14)
    Labeled: AGS (American Geographical Society), underlay and overlay, plate 35-C.
  - Philippines, north central Ifugao, 1972 (Box 15)
    Labeled: Area B = NC 1, 8 in 1, 1: 5,000, AGS.
  - Cordon, Luzon, Philippine Islands, 1963-1972; M-358 (Box 16–17)
    Label: Area I aerial photo coverage, 1: 50,000, paper underlay of combined AMS (Army Map Service, Corps of Engineers) sheets (hab + 1967), 1972; film overlay - air photo index; ISA/tg 1972, H's negs; PAF photography, 1963-1966.
  - Santos, 1969-1975; M-362, M-363, M-364X (Box 18)
    1: 50,000 MS and AS sheets: (M-362) overlay, Plate 4; (M-362) Santos, 1969 Apr 16, Plate 4, AP 54; (M-363) color tint elevation band overlay, 1969 Jun 9,Plate 4; (M-364X) Plate 5, District drainage, Ifugao, 1974; Plate 5, 3 small maps of Ifugao districts (1973-1975).
  - Pu'itan, Kinnakin, Bayninan (North Central Ifugao), Philippines, 1972 (Box 19)
    1: 5,000, from AGS (American Geographical Society) 1972 maps.
  - Mountain Province, Philippines, Circa 1970; M-65; 2; sheets (Box 19)
    1: 12,500, black and white, linear lined.
  - Sagada, Mountain Province, Philippines, 1963 (Box 20)
- Topical Files, 1897-1998; Series III
  Topical Files include professional events and organizations in which Conklin participated; research materials of colleagues Leonard Bloomfield, Frederick Russell Eggan, and Robert B. Fox; and materials relating to the Tasaday Controversy. (The Tasaday, an indigenous people of Mindanao, a Philippine island, were considered in the 1970s-1980s to be the last vestige of a stone age culture. The validity of this claim was questioned by anthropologists and journalists.)
  Materials are arranged by subject and alphabetically therein.
  - Bloomfield, Leonard
    - Ilocano
      - Conklin correspondence with Isadore Dyen, 1990 (Box 21, Folder 1)
      - Notebooks, 1941-1942 (Box 21, Folder 2-4)
      - Notes, boxed, 1941-1942 (Box 21, Folder 5-7)
      - Notes, loose, 1941-1942 (Box 21, Folder 8-9)
      - Text and text translations, manuscript, 1941-1942 (Box 21, Folder 10-13)
      - Text, typescript, 1941-1942 (Box 21, Folder 14-16)
      - Text translations, typescript, 1941-1942 (Box 21, Folder 17-19)
      - Vocabulary forms and formatives, 1941-1942 (Box 22–23)
        Consists of 2"x5" note cards, some with Slavic forms on the verso.
    - Tagalog précis (unpublished), Circa 1915 (Box 21, Folder 20)
  - Eggan, Fred
    - Assembly at University of Chicago, 1990-1991 (Box 24, Folder 1)
      Includes memorial brochure, HCC notes, and information on Eggan's papers.
    - Biographical writings
      - By Fred Eggan, 1978-1989 (Box 24, Folder 2)
      - By others, 1976-1991 (Box 24, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence
      - 1947-1948 (Box 24, Folder 4)
      - 1990-1991 (Box 24, Folder 5)
    - Department of Anthropology, University of Chicago
      - M.A. and Ph.D. list, 1897-1991 (Box 24, Folder 6)
      - Anthropology at Chicago: Tradition, Discipline, Department, 1979 (Box 24, Folder 6)
        Catalogue for exhibition marking the fiftieth anniversary of the Department of Anthropology, October 1979-February 1980.
    - Dinner at Field Museum, 1982 (Box 24, Folder 7)
    - Papers at University of Chicago Library: preliminary inventory, 1989-1991 (Box 24, Folder 8)
    - Philippine Studies Program annual reports, I-IX, 1953-1962 (Box 24, Folder 9)
    - Publications
      - Articles
        - 1941-1959 (Box 24, Folder 10)
        - 1960-1969 (Box 24, Folder 11)
        - 1974-1991 (Box 24, Folder 12)
      - Tinguian (and Ilocano) Dreams from Abra Province, Philippines, 1957 (Box 24, Folder 13)
  - Fox, Robert B.
    - Correspondence and clipping, 1985 (Box 24, Folder 14)
    - Notecards with bibliography and information on obituary, Circa 1985 (Box 25)
    - Obituary background and photographs, 1966-1985 (Box 24, Folder 15)
    - Obituary material, 1985-1987 (Box 24, Folder 16-17)
  - Professional events and organizations
    - American Academy of Arts and Sciences (AAAS), 1993-1997 (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - American Anthropological Association (AAA)
      - Annual meeting
        - Atlanta and Athens, Georgia, 1994 November 30-December 4 (Box 26, Folder 2)
        - New Orleans, LA, 1990 (Box 26, Folder 3)
        - Phoenix, AZ, 1988 November (Box 26, Folder 4)
        - San Francisco, CA, 1992 November (Box 26, Folder 5)
        - Washington, DC
          - 1985 December 4-8 (Box 26, Folder 6)
          - 1993 (Box 26, Folder 7)
          - 1995 November 15-19 (Box 26, Folder 8)
      - Correspondence, 1985-1996 (Box 26, Folder 9)
      - Language, Culture, and Ethnosemantics: A Mélange honoring David French, 1987 (Box 26, Folder 10)
      - Luncheon with visiting Vietnamese scholars, Washington, DC, 1989 November (Box 26, Folder 11)
      - Reception in honor of Lita Osmundsen, Philadelphia, PA, 1986 December (Box 26, Folder 12)
    - The Asia Society Philippines Council, 1963 November (Box 26, Folder 13)
    - L'Asie du Sud-Est et le Monde Insulindien (ASEMI), 1986 (Box 26, Folder 14)
    - Association for Asian Studies, Inc. (AAS), 1993-1995 (Box 26, Folder 15)
    - Cambridge University Press: Atran manuscript, 1985-1988 (Box 26, Folder 16)
    - Cultural Anthropology, Roy G. D'Andrade and David M. Schneider, 1981-1985 (Box 26, Folder 17)
    - Encyclopedia of World Cultures, David Levinson, ed., sponsored by Human Relations Area Files (HRAF) at Yale University, 1989-1992 (Box 26, Folder 18)
    - Food plants encyclopedia: Yale Encyclopedia of Food Sources: Plants, 1987-1988 (Box 26, Folder 19)
    - Fowler Museum, UCLA: Roy Hamilton, 1995-1996 (Box 26, Folder 20)
    - Freeman, J. D.: correspondence, 1981-1986 (Box 26, Folder 21)
      Includes material on Margaret Mead, R. Rappoport, Iban, and New Haven visit.
    - Fyssen Foundation Prize, Paris
      - Allocation, 1984 (Box 26, Folder 22)
      - Award, 1983-1984 (Box 26, Folder 23)
      - Award ceremony, 1984; 1 (Box 27)
        Conditions Governing Access
        Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
      - Award ceremony photographs, 1984 (Box 26, Folder 24)
      - Background, 1979-1984 (Box 26, Folder 25)
      - Correspondence, 1984-1986 (Box 26, Folder 26)
      - Diagrams (English), 1984 (Box 26, Folder 27)
      - Figures (and b. board), 1984 (Box 26, Folder 28)
      - Information packets, 1984 (Box 26, Folder 29)
      - Invitations, 1984 (Box 26, Folder 30)
      - Letters of regret, 1984 (Box 26, Folder 31)
      - MLA interview in Lettre d'Information: Culture, Sciences, Techniques, #8, French Embassy newsletter, 1984 April (Box 26, Folder 32)
      - Press coverage, 1984 (Box 26, Folder 33)
      - Remarks by Professor Conklin
        - English versions, 1984 (Box 26, Folder 34)
        - French versions, 1984 (Box 26, Folder 35)
    - Institute for Intercultural Studies (IIS)
      - Correspondence, mailing list, memoranda, 1987-1997 (Box 26, Folder 36)
      - Directors and committees, 1990-1996 (Box 26, Folder 37)
      - Meeting: George Mason University, 1997 (Box 26, Folder 38)
      - Meetings minutes, 1989-1993 (Box 26, Folder 39)
    - International Conference on Austronesian Linguistics (ICAL)
      - Auckland, New Zealand, fifth conference, 1988 January (Box 26, Folder 40)
      - Hawaii, sixth conference, 1991 May 20-24 (Box 26, Folder 41)
      - Leiden, seventh conference, 1994 August 22-27 (Box 26, Folder 42)
    - International Philippines Studies Conference (Fifth), Honolulu, Hawaii, 1996 April 14-16 (Box 26, Folder 43)
    - Lynch, Owen, World Resources Institute (WRI), 1993-1994 (Box 26, Folder 44)
      Correspondence concerning "slash and burn" mess and Ann Thrupp.
    - Museum of the American Indian, Iroquois publication, 1985 (Box 26, Folder 45)
    - National Academy of Sciences
      - Clips, correspondence, news release, 1987-1992 (Box 26, Folder 46)
      - Correspondence, 1984-1996 (Box 26, Folder 47)
      - Frake, Charles Oliver, 1986 (Box 26, Folder 48)
      - Lang, Serge, 1982-1989 (Box 26, Folder 49)
      - Lists and voting, 1980-1996 (Box 26, Folder 50)
      - Proposals for nomination, 1981-1993 (Box 26, Folder 51)
      - Whitney, William Dwight: conflict and resignation, 1991-1992 (Box 26, Folder 52)
    - National Geographic Society, 1990-1991 (Box 26, Folder 53)
    - New York Botanical Garden: Prance visit, 1986 (Box 26, Folder 54)
    - Olson, Sherry, McGill University, Geography Department, 1987 (Box 26, Folder 55)
    - Paper Institute, Atlanta, 1994 (Box 26, Folder 56)
    - Philippines Centennial Commission, 1996-1998 (Box 26, Folder 57)
    - Pinther, Everest, 1988 (Box 26, Folder 58)
    - Prizes and Awards
      - Bandelier Award, 1984-1985 (Box 26, Folder 59)
      - Cosmos Prize (Osaka, Japan), 1993-1994 (Box 26, Folder 60)
      - Fukuoka, Asian Cultural Prize Committee, 1990-1997 (Box 26, Folder 61)
      - MacArthur Foundation: correspondence, 1981-1990 (Box 26, Folder 62)
    - Sigma Xi, 1990 (Box 26, Folder 63)
    - Smithsonian: International Rice Research Institute travelling exhibit, 1985 (Box 26, Folder 64)
    - Social Science Research Council
      - Annual Report, 1993-1994 (Box 26, Folder 65)
      - Social Science Research Council: The First Fifty Years, by Elbridge Sibley, 1974 (Box 26, Folder 66)
    - Southeast Asia Studies (SEAS) conference: Other Indonesians, 1993 (Box 26, Folder 67)
    - Stanford University Press: George Sherman manuscript, 1987-1988 (Box 28, Folder 1)
    - Survival International - USA (SI-USA)
      - Correspondence, 1984-1991 (Box 28, Folder 2)
      - Minutes, 1984-1990 (Box 28, Folder 3)
      - Publications, Circa 1980-1989 (Box 28, Folder 4)
    - Trips
      - New York City, Newark, Philadelphia, Washington, D.C., 1993 March (Box 29, Folder 1)
      - St. Louis, MO, 1990 (Box 29, Folder 2)
    - Universiti Sains Malaysia, 1983-1986 (Box 29, Folder 3)
    - University of California, Berkeley
      - Anthropology Museum: Lowie, Hearst, 1992 (Box 29, Folder 4)
      - Newsletter, course and faculty information, 1985 (Box 29, Folder 5)
    - University of California Press: Martin Lewis book, 1991 (Box 29, Folder 6)
    - University of Chicago Press: History of Cartography, volume 2, book 2, by Schwartzberg, 1992 (Box 29, Folder 7)
    - University of Virginia: Peter Metcalf, 1986 (Box 29, Folder 8)
    - Wenner-Gren Foundation for Anthropological Research (WGFAR)
      - Address lists, 1986-1993 (Box 29, Folder 9)
      - Advisory Council
        - Minutes, 1986-1990 (Box 29, Folder 10-11)
        - Nominations for new members, 1986-1990 (Box 29, Folder 12)
      - Correspondence, 1986-1990 (Box 29, Folder 13)
      - Directories, 1988-1989 (Box 29, Folder 14)
      - Peters projection, 1985-1987 (Box 29, Folder 15)
  - Tagalog notecards
    - Nicknames, Circa 1952 (Box 30)
    - Vocabulary, Circa 1952
      - A-D (Box 31)
      - G-N (Box 32)
      - P-Y (Box 33)
  - Tasaday controversy
    - Asiaweek, 1986 June 15 (Box 34, Folder 1)
    - Articles
      - A-F, 1971-1989 (Box 34, Folder 2-3)
      - G-McL, 1971-1990 (Box 34, Folder 4)
      - Molony, 1972-1988 (Box 34, Folder 5)
      - M-Z, 1971-1990 (Box 34, Folder 6-7)
    - Articles and notes, 1991-1993 (Box 34, Folder 8)
    - Clippings, 1970-1990 (Box 34, Folder 9-10)
    - Correspondence, 1970-1989 (Box 34, Folder 11-13)
    - Cultural Survival Quarterly, vol. 15, #1, 1991 (Box 34, Folder 14)
    - Eggan and others, 1989-1990 (Box 34, Folder 15)
    - Elizalde, 1986-1988 (Box 34, Folder 16)
    - Legal, reports, 1987-1989 (Box 34, Folder 17)
    - National Geographic
      - Volume 140, #2, 1971 August (Box 34, Folder 18)
      - Volume 142, #2, 1972 August (Box 34, Folder 19)
    - Open letters and statements, 1986-1989 (Box 34, Folder 20)
    - Protecting Man's Right to Choice -- Panamin, 1972 (Box 34, Folder 21)
    - Random papers on the Tasaday, 1989 (Box 34, Folder 22)
    - Readings on the Tasaday, edited by Virginia B. Dandon, 1989 (Box 34, Folder 23)
    - Tasaday Documents, 1971 (Box 34, Folder 24)
    - A Tasaday Folio, by Jerome B. Bailen, 1986 (Box 34, Folder 25)
    - Tribal Forum, 1987 November-December (Box 34, Folder 26)